### SAMANTHA R. BALLARD

Srb146@miami.edu Samanthaballard.science LinkedIn

University of Miami Department of Applied Marine Physics/Ocean Sciences

#### **CURRENT POSITION**

# **University of Miami**

Doctoral Graduate Research Assistant

Miami, FL August 2015- Present

Scientist with experience in algorithm development, satellite data analysis, image processing, computational modeling and data science. Proficient skills utilizing synthetic aperture radar, nautical radar, active and passive remote sensing instruments, air and space-borne radar, satellites, atmospheric and oceanic models, and other instrumentation. Scientific programming and software development knowledge in MATLAB, Python, FORTRAN and IDL. Research interests are in computer vision, remote sensing, modeling, forecasting, data science and machine learning for Earth science (specifically atmosphere and ocean), planetary (space) science, and defense applications.

#### **EDUCATION**

**University of Miami** 

PhD, Applied Marine Physics/Ocean Sciences

Miami, FL Anticipated Graduation: Summer 2020

**Pennsylvania State University** 

BS, Meteorology. Chi Epsilon Pi

University Park, PA May 2015

### **COMPUTER LANGUAGES**

Python, Matlab, FORTRAN, IDL

# **GRANTS AND AWARDS**

**3<sup>rd</sup> Place in Earth Science for NASA Goddard's Summer Intern Poster Competition** NASA Goddard

#### Dean's Freshman Scholarship

Pennsylvania State University

## Chelius Family Scholarship in Meteorology

Pennsylvania State University

# Hans A. Panofsky Meteorology Scholarship

Pennsylvania State University

#### RESEARCH/WORK EXPERIENCE

#### **PhD Graduate Research Assistant**

Miami, FL

University of Miami, Advisor: Dr. Hans Graber, Dr. Roland Romeiser August 2

August 2015 – Present

Coastal Land Air Sea Interaction (CLASI) Experiment

Monterey Bay, CA

- Exploring air-sea interactions, turbulence, etc. in the coastal marine atmospheric boundary layer of Monterey Bay, California
- Goal: Combination of in-situ and remote sensing instruments to improve the Navy's Coupled Ocean Atmosphere Mesoscale Predication System (COAMPS) forecast model
- Primary experience with remote sensing satellite-based radar called Synthetic Aperture Radar (SAR) to study wind, waves etc., turbulence and other air-sea interactions
- Additional experience with coastal tower (anemometers), radiosondes, polarimetric cameras, buoys, ship wind and wave measurements, and forecast model
- Scientific analysis involves programming with MATLAB and Python perform mathematical transforms, statistical analysis, data manipulation and analysis, image processing and data visualization, and to develop algorithms to improve forecasting of air-sea parameters with models and satellites
- Improved coastal SAR wind retrieval algorithm
- Experience with atmospheric/oceanic model forecast and satellite data (SAR, NASA/NOAA) evaluation, analysis and depiction
- Mathematical transform analysis from in-situ, satellite and model wind data
- Applications to hurricane forecast research

#### NASA Goddard Intern

Synthetic Aperture Radar (SAR) Processing

Greenbelt, MD

Preliminary P-Band Wind Retrieval Algorithm using EcoSAR

June-August 2017

• Developed 1<sup>st</sup> successful P-Band SAR wind retrieval algorithm developed in Python using NASA's airborne radar, EcoSAR

# **NASA Advanced Computing for Earth Sciences (ACES)**

University of Virginia

June 2017

• 2.5 week bootcamp in Python, Fortran, and Super Computing (as well as other computer science topics like visualization, cloud computing, AI/machine learning etc.)

## **Research Cruise R/V Revelle**

Koror, Palau May 2016

FLEAT (Flow Encountering Abrupt Topography)

- Measured surface waves and small-scale flow patterns generating over the island-ridge system from ship-mounted X-band radar
- Used Doppler information to compute surface currents and wind speed

# **National Weather Service Meteorology Intern**

National Weather Service (NOAA)

University Park, PA January 2015- May 2015

- Used Python and GRADs to create graphics for case studies on winter storms affecting Pennsylvania in Winter, 2015
- Observed and helped with weather/hydrological forecasting shifts and radio/web broadcasts and updates

## **Solar and Space Physics REU**

Boulder, CO

University of Colorado Boulder

June 2014 - August 2014

- Research with Southwest Research Institute to automatically detect coronal mass ejections and other space weather research
- Programmed using IDL and HI (Heliospheric Imager) data from NASA's STEREO mission
- Created/Enhanced algorithm to automatically detect CMEs

### **Broadcast Meteorology Intern**

Fox 45 News

Baltimore, MD May 2013-August 2013

- Worked with morning meteorologist Jonathan Meyers
- Assisted with radio and on-screen forecasts
- Assisted in creation of weather forecasts and updated web information and social media posts
- Created resume reel of on-screen forecasts

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

### **Lab Coach/ Python Coding Instructor**

Miami, FL

Integrated Marine Program and College Training (IMPACT) Program

Summer 2019

- Lab coach for underprivileged, underrepresented incoming high school senior students
- Students shadowed for 6 weeks during the summer working on a research project
- Designed project based off of PhD research and python
- Taught Intro to Python for data science, scientific programming, machine learning (AI), and data visualization
- Students learned how to code, analyze and visualize scientific air-sea data from buoys, models and satellites
- Utilized NASA satellite data

• Final Presentation: Exploring the Air and Sea in Time and Space Using Buoy, Model and Satellite Data with Python

Miami, FL

Fall 2016

University Park, PA

Fall and Spring 2014

Severn, MD

Math/Science/Test Prep Elementary, Middle School and High School Tutor Miami, FL **Tutorial Resources** Fall 2017-Present

# **Forecasting Teaching Assistant**

Weather Forecasting (ATM 243) Miami, FL University of Miami Spring 2018

# **Oceanography Teaching Assistant**

Physical Oceanography (MSC 301) University of Miami

**Climate Teaching Assistant** 

University Park, PA

Understanding Global Climate Change (METEO 469) Spring 2015

Pennsylvania State University

**Advanced Math Tutor (College Level)** 

Differential Equations (MATH 251)

Pennsylvania State University

**Math Tutor (Elementary School Level)** 

5<sup>th</sup> Grade Summer 2014

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

S. Ballard, H. Graber, N. Laxague, M. Caruso and R. Romeiser "Advanced Extraction of Turbulent Scales for a New Technique Quantifying Air Sea Interaction Parameters" Journal of Geophysical Research. In Preparation

- S. Ballard, H. Graber, N. Laxague, M. Caruso and R. Romeiser "Exploring the Relationship Between SAR-Derived Wind Speeds and Surface Roughness Length Over the Ocean through Wavelet Analysis" 2019 IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS), Japan, 2019
- S. Ballard, H. Graber, M. Caruso and R. Romeiser "Comparison of X-Band SAR and COAMPS Model Wind Fields and Other Air Sea Interaction Parameters in Monterey Bay," 2018 IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS), Valencia Spain, 2018
- S. Ballard, H. Graber, M. Caruso and R. Romeiser (2018), "Coastal Applications of Wind and Wave Retrieval Using Synthetic Aperture Radar", 2018 Ocean Sciences Meeting, Portland, OR, 12-16 Feb.

S. Ballard, H. Graber and M. Caruso, "Coastal surface wind measurements derived from SAR," 2017 IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS), Fort Worth, TX, 2017, pp. 3629-3631.

doi: 10.1109/IGARSS.2017.8127785

#### PROFESSIONAL/CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

# **AGU Ocean Sciences Meeting (Oral)**

San Diego, CA

New Technique for Quantifying Air-Sea Interactions Using High Resolution SAR Imagery

Feb 2020

# **International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS) (Oral)**

Japan

**IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Society** 

July 2019

Exploring the Relationship Between SAR-Derived Wind Speeds and Surface Roughness Length Over the Ocean through Wavelet Analysis

# **European Space Agency's Living Planet Conference (Oral)**

Milan, Italy

May 2019

A Wavelet Technique to Derive Turbulent Air-Sea Structures near the coast from High Resolution SAR

## **American Geophysical Union Annual Meeting (AGU) (Poster)**

Washington DC

December, 2018

Characterizing Turbulent Air-Sea Interaction Phenomena in Coastal Environments by Wavelet Analysis of SAR-Derived Wind Fields

#### **International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)**

Valencia, Spain

IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Society

July 2018

Technical Program Chair: Remote Sensing of Coastal Areas II

#### International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS) (Poster)

IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Society

July 2018

Comparison of X-Band SAR and COAMPS Model Wind Fields and Other Air-Sea Interaction Parameters in Monterey Bay

## **AGU Ocean Sciences Meeting (Poster)**

Portland, OR

Coastal Applications of Wind and Wave Retrieval Using Synthetic Aperture Radar

Feb 2018

#### **AGU Ocean Sciences Meeting (Poster)**

Portland, OR

A Preliminary P-Band Wind Retrieval Algorithm Using EcoSAR

Feb 2018

### Naval Research Lab (Oral)

Washington, DC

Wind and Wave Retrievals Using Nautical Radar and SAR

Sept 2017

### **NASA Goddard Summer Intern Poster Competition**

Greenbelt, MD

A Preliminary P-Band Wind Retrieval Algorithm Using EcoSAR	August 2017
International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (Poster) IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Society Control Symfox Wind Managements Desired from SAR	Forth Worth, TX July 2017
Coastal Surface Wind Measurements Derived from SAR	September 2017
NASA Goddard Intern Presentation (Oral) Wind and Wave Retrievals Using SAR	Greenbelt, MD July 2017
NOAA National Hurricane Center (Oral)	Miami, Fl
SAR Applications in Tropical Cyclones	January 2017
OTHER PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE	
Office of Naval Research Project Meeting	Monterey Bay, CA
Presentation of PhD research with CLASI (PhD project) collaborators	May, 2018
International Society for Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing (ISPRS) TechnicalCommission III Symposium ReviewerBeijing, ChinaDevelopments, Technologies and Applications in Remote SensingJan 2018	
Mentoring Physical Oceanography Women to Increase Retention (MPOWIR) Miami,FL Monthly mentorship group for women in oceanography 2016-Present	
Weather Bug Private Sector Mentorship Program American Meteorological Society	MD 2014-2015
Undergraduate Leadership Workshop UCAR/NCAR	Boulder, CO June, 2014
Student Assistant for AMS 94rd annual meeting American Meteorological Society	Atlanta, GA February 2014
Student Assistant for AMS 93rd annual meeting American Meteorological Society	Austin, TX January 2013
Forecasting and Communications Shifts Campus Weather Service	University Park, PA 2012-2013

• Produced and recorded radio and TV broadcasts of Pennsylvania weather forecasts every week

# PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

Mentoring Physical Oceanography Women to Increase Retention (MPOWIR) American Meteorological Society (AMS) Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) American Geophysical Union (AGU)